<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shaun Finglas - 2012</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/2012.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2012-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Object Discovery</title><link href="/2012/12/object-discovery.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shaun Finglas</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-12-01:/2012/12/object-discovery.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently we had &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kevinrutherford"&gt;@kevinrutherford&lt;/a&gt;
in to talk about object discovery. While TDD is a great tool, it is no
excuse for some sort of design process. If you don't, you'll most
&lt;a href="http://devgrind.com/2007/04/25/how-to-not-solve-a-sudoku/"&gt;likely end up with a
mess&lt;/a&gt;. This
session was based around this principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One point that was discussed what …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently we had &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kevinrutherford"&gt;@kevinrutherford&lt;/a&gt;
in to talk about object discovery. While TDD is a great tool, it is no
excuse for some sort of design process. If you don't, you'll most
&lt;a href="http://devgrind.com/2007/04/25/how-to-not-solve-a-sudoku/"&gt;likely end up with a
mess&lt;/a&gt;. This
session was based around this principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One point that was discussed what that the first few seconds of a test
for a new class is the most important part of the TDD process. It is
here where you will decide whether to take a state or interaction based
approach to testing. This first test will dictate the structure of the
new class. Once you start with tests, it becomes difficult to evolve or
change the design of a class without friction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is generally two types of code at Codeweavers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/Finglas/4a9e9d35d64c150d6075.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick comes from the fact that just because you use C#/Java/etc..
most of the time you aren't actually writing OO code. You often end up
writing procedural code in a rather obtuse manner. A takeaway from this
afternoon was to try and perform more CRC
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Class-responsibility-collaboration_card"&gt;(class-responsibility-collaborator)&lt;/a&gt;sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;CRC (Object Cube)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this session we performed a modified version of a CRC. One thing
I always find with CRC sessions is how useful they are. The problem I
and others find is when it comes to day to day development, I'm too
eager to start coding without performing some sort of up front design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Events&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to write flexible OO code, you need to hide as much state as
possible. While this is great in practice it turns out to be very
difficult to achieve in the real world. One method of getting around
this is to make use of events aka the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Observer_pattern"&gt;observer
pattern&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kevin used a wiki as an example. Consider a page that is updated. If
this page was to fire a changed event, then anything that is listening
for these events would be notified. The observers could then react once
the event was received. The nice thing about this approach is that the
code obeys the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open/closed_principle"&gt;open/closed
principle&lt;/a&gt;. New
features can be added without the need for the change to have a large,
rippling effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Nouns and Namespaces&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was first exposed to object oriented programming, apart from
believing that inheritance was the coolest aspect of OO, I was also led
to believe that using nouns when designing classes can be useful. It
turned out that this was a fallacy. If you follow this advice you'll end
up with a small collection of classes that do everything. The biggest
revelation I had during the session came from the importance of
namespaces. Using nouns for up front design can be extremely useful if
you remember that the noun can potentially be a namespace. This means
you'll end up with a handful of namespaces that are relevant to the
domain in question. Inside these namespaces you will have one or more
classes that do &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single_responsibility_principle"&gt;one thing, and one thing
well.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Closing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the session I was left with many questions and new ideas
to test and try out. Using events to hide state, yet allow other objects
to interact when required was a real eye opener. However it turns out
that when actually trying to implement these ideas in code, it is
actually quite difficult due to my current thinking. The plan for the
next month will be to explore these ideas in more detail and see what
affect it has on my day to day development.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="programming"></category></entry><entry><title>Codeweavers Code Retreat</title><link href="/2012/10/codeweavers-code-retreat.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Shaun Finglas</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-10-01:/2012/10/codeweavers-code-retreat.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week we had &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kevinrutherford"&gt;@kevinrutherford&lt;/a&gt;
in to run a coderetreat. It was the first retreat I've taken part in
personally, the same applying to much of the team. The day was to focus
on one challenge - &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_Game_of_Life"&gt;Conway's Game of
Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; though
each iteration would introduce new constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Iteration 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week we had &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kevinrutherford"&gt;@kevinrutherford&lt;/a&gt;
in to run a coderetreat. It was the first retreat I've taken part in
personally, the same applying to much of the team. The day was to focus
on one challenge - &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_Game_of_Life"&gt;Conway's Game of
Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; though
each iteration would introduce new constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Iteration 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four &lt;a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?XpSimplicityRules"&gt;rules of simple
code&lt;/a&gt; were discussed, aka
"Extreme Normal Form".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passes tests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communicates intent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No duplication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nothing unncessary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first run through was somewhat of a disaster. We became too obsessed
with how the grid was to be stored. This meant we spent a long time
messing around with arrays and multidemionsal arrays in C#. Both are
somewhat tedious and not something we use often, therefore we concluded
a more "grid agnostic" approach would be needed. After all, there is
nothing stating the grid need be a square, fixed layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Iteration 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of &lt;a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?ArrangeActAssert"&gt;Arrange, Act,
Assert&lt;/a&gt; or AAA was discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arrange - set up pre conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Act - do something on the subject under test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assert - verify or check some result&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constraint during this iteration was that all asserts were to be
created first, and we would work backwards. Personally I found this
difficult, both mentally and in terms of tooling. For the past four
years I've rarely wrote an assert first, therefore this switch proved
tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visual Studio and Resharper also tend to favour a top down approach. In
other words, it's easier to stub out a class and add methods, rather
than the inverse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New members to the team found the act of writing the assert first much
easier however, and they're looking to continue this in day to day
development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point I took from here is that while I may personally know what I'm
writing, my partner might not be aware of where we are heading. Starting
with the assert first allows both developers to see the goal for that
particular test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Iteration 3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our third iteration introduced the unrealistic concept of mute pairing.
Only the code and tests can reveal our intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using ping ponging (switching between developers who writes
tests/production code) we managed to get a good chunk of functionality
complete. Despite this the rest of the iteration was very difficult.
Being unable to talk about design concepts was incredibly frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important concept we took away from here was that more than
likely the developer working with your code tomorrow will not have
worked with you previously. That means any conversations you've had to
explain the code will be lost. The only thing left to communicate will
be your tests or production code. Due to this observation, it is cruicly
we name our tests and code in a manner that is cleary and
understandable, whether six minutes or six months have passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Iteration 4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our fourth iteration had a focus on OO concepts. Up until now, our code
had exposed much of the state in various ways. The challenge was to
focus on the messages that are exchanged between objects, rather the
change in state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This introduced a new problem. How do we test an object without exposing
state? We talked about a couple of methods; mock objects or the &lt;a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?SelfShuntPattern"&gt;self
shunt pattern&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the shelf shunt pattern was an enjoyable experience - we
identified numerous violations of the &lt;a href="http://www.giorgiosironi.com/2009/09/solid-part-4-interface-segregation.html"&gt;interface segregation
principle&lt;/a&gt;
as it was actually painful to add to the interface in question. With
mocking frameworks this pain is often lessened due to the dynamic and
often "magic" constructs they employ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally I found code writting using this pattern easier to
understand. The plan will be to adopt this approach for a month or so
and see how it effects day to day development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our code looked pretty good at this point, though we were struggling to
replace a conditional statement. After a few minutes the idea seemed
obvious once we recieved a hint -
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polymorphism_in_object-oriented_programming"&gt;polymorphism&lt;/a&gt;.
This sparked a nice discussion about the "&lt;a href="http://www.antiifcampaign.com/"&gt;Anti
If&lt;/a&gt;" campaign - another point I'm
looking to take further. This iteration proved the most challenging for
the whole team. A second run through allowed further progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Iteration 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final round had us regroup with our original partners. Here we could
use any approach and see how far we could progress. Me and my partner
opted for a failing acceptance test, from here we would implement the
functionality top down until we had the components wired together. This
worked well until we struggled to test how the cells were stored without
exposing any state needlessly. The solution came from some discussion
around &lt;a href="http://www.markhneedham.com/blog/2008/11/06/object-calisthenics-first-thoughts/"&gt;object
calesethenics&lt;/a&gt;
– first class collections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing to note was how drastically different our code looked, when
compared to the first iteration. During the course of the day we all
noticed a difference in our overall approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I believe I speak for the whole team when I say how much we
enjoyed the day. It was refreshing to spend a whole day coding, rather
than being interuppted with other issues. Naturally this was quite
tiring - though left lots energy for discussion afterwards. As a
conclusion it would appear that as a collective we need to spend more
time each week carrying out deliberate practice. For new starters this
is essential training, while for more seasoned developers this is a
useful way to keep our skillset up to date.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="programming"></category></entry><entry><title>MVC is Broken</title><link href="/2012/10/mvc-is-broken.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Shaun Finglas</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-10-01:/2012/10/mvc-is-broken.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you look up the definition of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model_view_controller"&gt;MVC or Model View
Controller&lt;/a&gt;, it will
hail the definition as being able to change your front end without
affecting other parts of the application and vice versa. This sounds
great in theory, however this claim is nothing more than a &lt;em&gt;blatant
lie …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you look up the definition of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model_view_controller"&gt;MVC or Model View
Controller&lt;/a&gt;, it will
hail the definition as being able to change your front end without
affecting other parts of the application and vice versa. This sounds
great in theory, however this claim is nothing more than a &lt;em&gt;blatant
lie&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A failing of the architectural pattern comes from the whole codebase
being tied to a specific stack. Take ASP.NET MVC. The domain logic will
most likely be in C#. Therefore your models will be in C#. Your
controllers will be in C#. Your views will be a mixture of C# and some
form of a templating language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to change your stack to the "next big thing" you are forced
to take a big bang approach. ASP.NET MVC &lt;em&gt;won't be around forever&lt;/em&gt;.
Being tied to a specific technology feels wrong. Therefore this coupling
means your designers are forced to use the templating language that your
framework supports. This should be a flexible option that should be easy
to change, after all the MVC pattern states this as one of it's
benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being tied to a specific technology leads onto our most recent project.
One of our biggest and most important projects is a legacy Flash
application. Back in the early 2000's it was a cutting edge application
- consistent across all browsers, ajax style requests, responsive
design, you name it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said we all know Flash is on its way out, and there lies the
problem. It took myself about two weeks to add a few text boxes to the
app in my first year at Codeweavers, all because the UI code is so
difficult to work with. The &lt;em&gt;logic is mixed within the UI&lt;/em&gt;. Had the app
been developed in a MVC style we would be in a position to replace the
legacy UI with a modern alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We make use of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Service-oriented_architecture"&gt;SOA or Service Oriented
Architecture&lt;/a&gt;
at Codeweavers, therefore it seemed a natural fit to apply this to our
rewrite of our legacy application. I proposed a theory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;"for an application to be truly independent of the frontend and
backend the code must be developed in different languages."&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I taught myself enough PHP to make a JSON request, perform
some conditional logic and loop over a collection. With this I was able
to recreate one of our applications that was powered by our backend C#
services. &lt;a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2012/06/the-php-singularity.html"&gt;I would not want to create an application in
PHP&lt;/a&gt;,
but using PHP as a templating language was a great fit. After all this
is one of the intentions of the language. Limiting myself to just three
simple PHP constructs I was &lt;em&gt;forced to put all logic on the service&lt;/em&gt; in
question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This complete separation of concerns is made possible due to the fact it
is simply not possible for code to leak between the layers due to the
different languages used in the implementation. This means I could
easily spin up numerous front end views while the backend remains
unchanged. Likewise we could change the back end implementation from C#
to another language. Providing the endpoints and request/responses
match, the front end will still be functional. This full separation of
concerns is what MVC style frameworks have &lt;em&gt;failed to achieve&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ten years from now it is hard to say what the web will look like.
What I can guarantee is that the web will still be here. We'll still be
making HTTP requests. We'll still be making back end services that
powers much of the apps on the internet. One thing no one can really
comment on is what the web will look like. One point we all could agree
on is that HTML5 should be wide spread and no doubt "&lt;em&gt;the next big
thing&lt;/em&gt;" will be on the horizon. The great thing by taking the approach
discussed previously is that Codeweavers will be in the position to
change either the front end or back end of our codebase at any time.
Precisely what the MVC pattern has failed to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="retro"></category></entry><entry><title>Recommended Reading 2012</title><link href="/2012/10/recommended-reading-2012.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Shaun Finglas</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-10-01:/2012/10/recommended-reading-2012.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here is my updated reading list for 2012. We might have missed something
so if you think we should be reading it, let us know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0071392319?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0071392319"&gt;The Toyota
    Way&lt;/a&gt; -
    Jeffrey Liker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0566086654?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0566086654"&gt;The
    Goal&lt;/a&gt; -
    Eli Goldratt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0321278658?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0321278658"&gt;XP
    Explained&lt;/a&gt;-
    Kent Beck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Pragmatic-Programmer-Andrew-Hunt/dp/020161622X"&gt;The Pragmatic
    Programmer&lt;/a&gt;-
    Andrew Hunt and David Thomas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/The-Clean-Coder-Professional-ebook/dp/B0050JLC9Y"&gt;The Clean
    Coder …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here is my updated reading list for 2012. We might have missed something
so if you think we should be reading it, let us know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0071392319?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0071392319"&gt;The Toyota
    Way&lt;/a&gt; -
    Jeffrey Liker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0566086654?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0566086654"&gt;The
    Goal&lt;/a&gt; -
    Eli Goldratt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0321278658?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0321278658"&gt;XP
    Explained&lt;/a&gt;-
    Kent Beck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Pragmatic-Programmer-Andrew-Hunt/dp/020161622X"&gt;The Pragmatic
    Programmer&lt;/a&gt;-
    Andrew Hunt and David Thomas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/The-Clean-Coder-Professional-ebook/dp/B0050JLC9Y"&gt;The Clean
    Coder&lt;/a&gt; -
    Robert C. Martin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0132350882?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0132350882"&gt;Clean Code - Robert C.
    Martin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0321146530?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0321146530"&gt;Test-Driven
    Development&lt;/a&gt;
    by Kent Beck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0201485672?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0201485672"&gt;Refactoring - Martin
    Fowler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0321109295?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0321109295"&gt;Refactoring Workbook - William
    Wake&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0321127420?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0321127420"&gt;Patterns of Enterprise Application
    Architecture&lt;/a&gt; -
    Martin Fowler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0596007124?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0596007124"&gt;Head First Design
    Patterns&lt;/a&gt; -
    Freeman, et al&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0321503627?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=philipmead-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0321503627"&gt;Growing Object-Oriented Software, Guided by
    Tests&lt;/a&gt; -
    Steve Freeman and Nat Pryce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Things-Every-Programmer-Should-Know/dp/0596809484"&gt;97 Things Every Programmer Should
    Know&lt;/a&gt;-
    Kevlin Henney&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Pro-ASP-NET-MVC-Framework-ebook/dp/B005PZ07US"&gt;Pro ASP.NET MVC
    x+&lt;/a&gt; -
    Steve Sanderson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Framework-Design-Guidelines-Conventions-ebook/dp/B0017SWPNO"&gt;Framework Design
    Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; -
    Brad Abrams and Krzysztof Cwalina&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="reading"></category></entry><entry><title>The Problem with Auto Updating Browsers</title><link href="/2012/06/the-problem-with-auto-updating-browsers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Shaun Finglas</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-06-01:/2012/06/the-problem-with-auto-updating-browsers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing the latest version of Firefox (version 13) has
just been released. Bear in mind that a week ago I updated our Selenium
bindings so that we could use Firefox 9+ for running our browser tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest release is another great release for the Firefox …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing the latest version of Firefox (version 13) has
just been released. Bear in mind that a week ago I updated our Selenium
bindings so that we could use Firefox 9+ for running our browser tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest release is another great release for the Firefox team, except
there is software out there will be broken. The software in question I'm
talking about is any code that uses &lt;a href="http://seleniumhq.org/download/"&gt;Selenium
2.22.0&lt;/a&gt; that was released 2012-05-29.
It turns out the bindings only work for Firefox 12 or less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For whatever reason any tests that used Selenium this morning just
stopped working for us - &lt;a href="http://groups.google.com/group/selenium-users/browse_thread/thread/83a7895693364c3a"&gt;and
others&lt;/a&gt;.
The tests in question caused the runner to hang as no window could be
opened. I'm not sure what causes this, as the browser is essentially the
same to the end user, bar some new features. Not being a Selenium
developer I cannot comment how or why this has happened, nor can I
suggest the Selenium team should be version agnostic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our solution in the end was simple. Turn off the auto updating and
downgrade the browser. &lt;a href="https://blog.shaunfinglas.co.uk/2011/12/how-to-achieve-more-stable-end-to-end.html"&gt;I've blogged about this in the
past&lt;/a&gt;,
but since Firefox 10 - the team are adopting a "silent" update process.
This is great for end users. Imagine the countless man hours saved if
IE6 had shipped with an auto update feature? The problem now seems to be
in the hands of developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another attempt to make this problem more obvious has been to add a
check prior to our tests running to ensure that it can open a window. If
this fails or hangs, we display a useful error message indicating that
the browser in question is not compatible. This is due to the fact that
it is not immediately obvious what the problem is. More confusion occurs
when some machines will execute the tests with no problems at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools -&amp;gt; Options -&amp;gt; Advanced -&amp;gt; Update Tab&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you use Selenium and Firefox - ditch the auto updating. Manually
update your bindings and check compatability for now...&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="testing"></category></entry><entry><title>Achieving more Isolated Unit Testing</title><link href="/2012/05/achieving-more-isolated-unit-testing.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-05-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-05-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Shaun Finglas</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-05-01:/2012/05/achieving-more-isolated-unit-testing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Good&lt;/em&gt; unit tests should be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;independent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;well focused&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;isolated&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your unit tests are slow, you're not gonna run them as often as you
should. Therefore one of the main benefits of unit testing is lost - the
lack of instant feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of your unit tests should be independent …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Good&lt;/em&gt; unit tests should be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;independent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;well focused&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;isolated&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your unit tests are slow, you're not gonna run them as often as you
should. Therefore one of the main benefits of unit testing is lost - the
lack of instant feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of your unit tests should be independent. The order in which you
run your tests should not matter. By keeping your tests focused you
should be able to refactor, add new code and not have the majority of
your tests fail. If you change class A, you would expect class A's tests
to fail at worst. If other tests outside of this scope fail, your tests
are not focused enough. This lack of focus leads on to isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tests should be isolated from other dependencies. Dependencies such as
other classes should not affect each other, providing the contract
between the code is maintained. Likewise the file system, the web and
databases should not be involved anywhere with your unit tests. If any
of these dependencies come into play, you're not unit testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Codeweavers we have around &lt;strong&gt;ten thousand tests&lt;/strong&gt;, with unit tests
accounting for the majority of these tests. Naturally this means every
now and then we take time to do a bit of house keeping regarding our
tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing we noticed was that some of our tests were taking longer to
run than other tests. They were taking anywhere from one to ten seconds.
Ten seconds for a unit test is a huge time. During this period we could
have run hundreds of other tests! As for why these tests took so long to
run? Easy. They were not unit tests. Code had been added that broke that
layer of isolation. Some tests were hitting real web services for
example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to be fully isolated I proposed a simply solution. &lt;strong&gt;Unplug the
network cable&lt;/strong&gt;. Any tests that failed would not be unit tests. This
gave us one of two options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refactor the code - remove or stub the dependencies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promote the tests to integration/regression tests (only run prior to
    check in)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can take this idea one step further. Next time you run your tests
try running them from a different location. Any tests that fail are
relying on relative/hardcoded paths and will need attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After performing this task on our codebase we had some failures. The
nice thing about solving these failures is that our tests now run a lot
faster. Our slowest tests are now end to end regression tests which are
only run prior to check in or by our CI server. We've also made sure
that from a disaster recover point of view, we can continue developing
locally even if our CI server is not present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So take the experiment. Unplug your computer from the network. How many
of your "unit tests" fail?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tdd"></category><category term="unit-testing"></category></entry><entry><title>Recursively Building a Web Service using the same Web Service</title><link href="/2012/03/recursively-building-web-service-using.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shaun Finglas</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-03-01:/2012/03/recursively-building-web-service-using.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back during the later part of 2011 there was a common theme occurring in
our retrospectives each week. How can we replicate our live environment
as close as possible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We took steps to achieve this goal by creating a single machine image to
ensure all our machines were configured correctly …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back during the later part of 2011 there was a common theme occurring in
our retrospectives each week. How can we replicate our live environment
as close as possible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We took steps to achieve this goal by creating a single machine image to
ensure all our machines were configured correctly. Another quick win was
to ensure certain aspects of our live data was restored to our local
development databases during the night. This enabled us to take stack
traces from our logs, and quite literally paste them into our IDE and
replicate the users problem instantly. Without the same data set we
could have seen different results. Despite these positive steps, there
was a missing link in our replication process. How do we simulate the
traffic of our live environment? As an example, we average anywhere from
four to five thousand calculations per minute with our current web
services, with our local and demo environment no where near this figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During 2011 I found myself involved in many deployments in which despite
heavy testing I was uneasy. On our demo environments we could throw the
same amount of load against our services, yet sometime after deploying
our service would fall over. We would quickly have to revert and go back
to the drawing board. The problem we had despite our traffic being
mimicked in terms of volume was the load was not real. Our customers
however have many more variations of requests that we were simply not
predicting. The other obvious issue was during local development, the
service may well handle the same volume of traffic, yet once live and
the process has been running for a few hours - things might go bump.
Factors such as memory or timeouts being the culprits here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collectively we had a few ideas on how to solve this. We looked into low
level solutions such as directing traffic from IIS/apache towards other
servers. We examined other load testing tools, and we even contemplated
creating our own load creator. This internal tool would go over our
database and fire off a number of requests at our demo environment. I
felt uneasy with all these solutions. They were not "real" enough. I
wanted the real time traffic to be submitted to our demo services, only
then could we have full confidence in our work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My idea was rather radical in the sense it was so easy, yet dangerous
enough that it might just work. I proposed we integrated our own
service, into itself. In other words, just before our service returns
the results of the calculation, it takes the users request and submits
it again, against our demo environment. The same service would be
recursively submitting into itself. In order to ensure we did not affect
the speed of the service, the submission is performed via an async call,
meaning if this second call was to die the live service would be
unaffected. The obvious downside here was that in order to test this, we
needed to deploy the changes to our live service. This was achieved via
a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feature_toggle"&gt;feature toggle&lt;/a&gt;, meaning
at any time we could turn the feature on or off without affecting any
customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end result of this was that when the feature is enabled, the traffic
on our live service is sent to our demo service. This allows us to
deploy experimental or new features and changes to the demo environment
and check them under real load, with real time data. If all goes well
after a period of time we can deploy to our live service, if not we roll
back and no one is the wiser.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="testing"></category></entry><entry><title>Warnings as Errors</title><link href="/2012/02/warnings-as-errors.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-02-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-02-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shaun Finglas</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-02-01:/2012/02/warnings-as-errors.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One thing that annoyed me when starting at Codeweavers was the amounts
of warnings that would occur during a build of any of our projects.
Seeing the build progress only to spew out a screenful of text was
something that did not sit right with me. I was not the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One thing that annoyed me when starting at Codeweavers was the amounts
of warnings that would occur during a build of any of our projects.
Seeing the build progress only to spew out a screenful of text was
something that did not sit right with me. I was not the only one who
felt this was wrong, but as there was so many warnings in some cases, it
was easier just to pretend they were not there. After all everything was
working fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2005/06/the-broken-window-theory.html"&gt;broken window
theory&lt;/a&gt;
is very much in action here. During our last standards review we decided
that there should ideally be zero warnings per project. It is worth
mentioning that most of our warnings were just that, warnings about
something that was not really a major issue. Warnings such as unused
variables and so on fall into this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, while 90% of our warnings were ignorable, there were
a handful which were rather important. Examples such as referencing
different versions of required .dlls. Warnings like this are extremely
helpful. It would be wrong for these to be hidden among a block of less
serious issues. Warnings such as these once visible, can save hours of
painful debugging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of our projects had a fair few warnings - in the region of fifty
plus. In order to begin tackling these larger projects we started
slowly. If in a single day I would have removed a batch of warnings,
this was a step in the right direction. After a week or so all our
projects were void of warnings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step was to make sure we do not go back to having larger
projects with warnings galore. To prevent this I enabled "&lt;strong&gt;Treat
warnings as errors&lt;/strong&gt;" within Visual Studio. This is per project setting
and can be found under the "&lt;strong&gt;Build&lt;/strong&gt;" tab. Do note that you must enable
this for "&lt;strong&gt;All Configurations&lt;/strong&gt;" otherwise any settings you change will
only apply to Debug/Release builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like this feature of Visual Studio immensely. Having the compilier do
as much work as possible - in this case check for warnings is similar to
a tip found in &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Working-Effectively-Legacy-Code-ebook/dp/B0017DQ8KU/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1329313155&amp;amp;sr=8-3"&gt;Working Effectively with Legacy
Code&lt;/a&gt;.
Here the concept of "leaning on the compiler" is introduced. In other
words you introduce an error in order to show you the usages of a piece
of code - this is stark contrast to manually searching for the code in
question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end result of this process is now during a build, if any warnings
occur, the build will fail. The build will report where the warning is,
along with why there is a problem. While this is great in theory it can
cause some slight pain when developing, as you may comment out some code
to experiment only to find the build failing due to unused variables.
Despite this treating warnings as errors has been a great help. Recently
we have solved some pretty serious issues with regards third party
dependencies all thanks to treating warnings as errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The idea of allowing the computer to do as much work as possible
applies to all languages. For your compiler/interpreter etc... there
will be an option to apply warnings. This is not a specific language
feature.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="programming"></category></entry><entry><title>Log Everything</title><link href="/2012/01/log-everything.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shaun Finglas</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-01-01:/2012/01/log-everything.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally conceived back in mid 2011, starting a new
project made me think back to this event, hence the post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any developer worth their salt will know what logging is. You could
argue there are two types of logging, either developer logging or
auditing. Developer logging would …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally conceived back in mid 2011, starting a new
project made me think back to this event, hence the post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any developer worth their salt will know what logging is. You could
argue there are two types of logging, either developer logging or
auditing. Developer logging would be what we log when something goes
wrong. Using the results of this logging we can track down what went
wrong, and put fixes in place to stop this event from occurring again.
If this logging fails, or logs the incorrect thing it is not the end of
the world. Due to this, I generally do not care for testing such
scenarios. The code should behave the same with our without this
logging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auditing would come under logging which as part of the application needs
to be carried out at all times. Consider visiting a cash machine. When
withdrawing fifty pounds, you want to make sure your bank logs this in
case anything goes wrong. This sort of logging is crucial, and must work
and must log the correct data. This is considered a feature, therefore
this should be tested as it is part of the behavior of the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I think back to my first few years of programming my code was
littered with logging. In the early days after each statement, variable
and function I would print out what happened, along with any errors that
happened. In fact I'd say that everyone starts out like this. The
strange thing is as we get better, the logging becomes less and less.
Rather than the first class citizen we relied on in the early days,
logging is seen as boring. The problem with treating logging code as a
second class citizen is that when things go wrong, it can be very
difficult or near impossible to track down what has happened. When you
realise you need logging, its often too late. You will need to redeploy
the application and wait for the problem to expose itself again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2011 we had a difficult problem to track down. The dreaded
"&lt;code&gt;OutOfMemoryException&lt;/code&gt;". Being the cocky developers we were, we decided
to add the logging last. After all, it was there for when things went
wrong. We never planned things would go wrong, after all it "&lt;em&gt;worked on
my machine&lt;/em&gt;". After redeploying the application with logging we managed
to track down roughly what was going wrong, and in turn began to resolve
the problem. Had we added this logging initially, we could have resolved
this problem in half the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson I learned here was simple. Any time you have an error, log
it. If the logging is not in place, we add it. Creating a new
application? In the first iteration(s) make sure some form of logging is
in place. I believe by following this simple rule any future issues can
be handled easier. Logging should be a first class citizen regardless of
purpose.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="programming"></category></entry><entry><title>Write Unit Tests? Start deleting them</title><link href="/2012/01/write-unit-tests-start-deleting-them.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2012-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shaun Finglas</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-01-01:/2012/01/write-unit-tests-start-deleting-them.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A recent &lt;a href="http://blog.steveklabnik.com/posts/2011-09-22-extracting-domain-models-a-practical-example"&gt;blog post by Steve
Klabnik&lt;/a&gt;
concluded with a statement about tossing unit tests if you have end to
end tests covering the code in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't be afraid to change the tests! As soon as you've verified that
you've transcribed the code correctly, don't be afraid to just …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A recent &lt;a href="http://blog.steveklabnik.com/posts/2011-09-22-extracting-domain-models-a-practical-example"&gt;blog post by Steve
Klabnik&lt;/a&gt;
concluded with a statement about tossing unit tests if you have end to
end tests covering the code in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't be afraid to change the tests! As soon as you've verified that
you've transcribed the code correctly, don't be afraid to just nuke
things and start again. Especially if you have integration level tests
that confirm that your features actually work, your unit tests are
expendable. If they're not useful, kill them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few people on Twitter found this odd, and I'd have included myself in
this statement a while back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/isaacsanders"&gt;@isaacsanders&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/avdi"&gt;@avdi&lt;/a&gt; seeing
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KentBeck"&gt;@KentBeck&lt;/a&gt; delete unit tests during his
screencasts changed my TDD process forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Shaun Finglas (@F1nglas) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/F1nglas/statuses/160776765353111552"&gt;January 21,
2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pragprog.com/screencasts/v-kbtdd/test-driven-development"&gt;Kent Beck's TDD
screencasts&lt;/a&gt;
changed my view on deleting unit tests however. During the later videos,
he actually deleted some tests. Pretty much all TDD resources don't
really mention this. One of the key points beginners learn is that if
you break any tests, you've introduced a regression. This is not always
the case. If you follow the rule of never deleting ANY tests you
encounter you are going to be stuck with someone else's implementation
forever. Likewise unit tests are there to drive design, not enforce how
something works. I remember discussing deleting unit tests with my work
colleagues and finding Kent's videos pretty shocking at the time. I mean
deleting unit tests!?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more I do TDD, the less this statement becomes so jarring. For
example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/Finglas/217feb75bc8facf38534.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider a test for the above behavior, such as we get the result back
in a particular state. Pretend the logic is rather simple, and it does
not warrant a separate object. Any other developer should be free to
come along and change the internals of this method. As long as we get a
result back in the correct state, the test should be valid. The test
should not care that we are using strings, lists or whatever internally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasionally I find tests like this hard to pass. In other words, I feel
like the logic is correct yet the test fails. Maybe I'm using a new
language feature, or a language feature that seems to be not working as
I expected. If so I'll break out a new unit test that tests the
implementation. Such tests are often refereed to as &lt;a href="http://blog.thecodewhisperer.com/2011/12/14/when-to-write-learning-tests/"&gt;learning
tests&lt;/a&gt;.
Here with a smaller focus I often become aware of what I'm doing wrong.
Following Kent Becks example, I ditch the test after and move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel this sums up my feelings nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ELLIOTTCABLE"&gt;@elliottcable&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/F1nglas"&gt;@F1nglas&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/isaacsanders"&gt;@isaacsanders&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KentBeck"&gt;@kentbeck&lt;/a&gt; let them [tests] guide you
to a design but don't let them hold you to a design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Avdi Grimm (@avdi) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/avdi/statuses/160780747827974145"&gt;January 21,
2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I and others are not saying bin every unit test you have that is covered
by end to end tests. Unit tests are great, you can run hundreds in a
matter of seconds. They have their place as part of the development
process, but do not find yourself working against them. However I am
saying you should delete any test which relies on implementation
details. I am saying bin any test which does not make sense. I am also
saying bin tests as part of a refactoring session as long as you have
test coverage higher up. If you don't have test coverage such as
acceptance tests, you cannot be sure you have not broke anything after
the refactor.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="programming"></category><category term="tdd"></category><category term="unit-testing"></category></entry></feed>